Guide to the African American Jazz Preservation Society of Pittsburgh Oral History Project Records and Recordings, 1995-1999 AIS.1998.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
African American Jazz Preservation Society of Pittsburgh Oral History Project Records and Recordings
1995-1999
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Afro-American Musical Association of Pittsburgh
AIS.1998.04
72 cassette_tapes (plus 4 mss boxes)
This oral history collection consists of transcripts, cassette tapes, project working files and background organizational records of the interviews conducted during the African American Jazz Preservation Society of Pittsburgh (AAJPSP) Oral History Project (1995-1999). The project documents individual African American Jazz Musicians in Pittsburgh as well as their efforts to organize. The content of the interviews span from 1904 to 1999.
History
The Pittsburgh African American Musicians' Association was incorporated as a non-profit organization in Allegheny County, Court of Common Pleas 1906. In 1908, the American Federation of Labor granted Black musicians in Pittsburgh a charter to form Local 471 of the American Federation of Musicians (AFM), also known as the Musicians Protective Union. In 1965, as a result of the new ALF-CIO desegregation policy, Local 471 was merged with AFM Local 60 to form AFM Local 60-471, also known as the Pittsburgh Musical Society and then later as the Pittsburgh Musicians Union.
Local 471 was located in a club on Wylie Avenue in the Hill District of Pittsburgh. The club had offices on the first floor, with a piano bar and rehearsal space on the second floor. The club was a popular gathering place for musicians, both local and national, offering a congenial atmosphere for rehearsing and jamming. The organization was a powerful force in the development of community in the city's African American neighborhoods and the securing of economic and educational opportunities for local musicians and bands. Union members played in theaters, clubs, restaurants, ice follies, vaudeville acts, touring companies, churches and concert halls throughout Pittsburgh, the continental U.S., Western Europe, Canada, Mexico, and the Caribbean.
When the Civic Arena was built in the mid-1950s, much of the lower Hill District of Pittsburgh was torn down, including the musicians' club, forcing the union to move temporarily to a storefront on Centre Avenue in East Liberty. More permanently the union found space in a former bar on the corner of Enterprise and Frankstown Avenues, also in East Liberty. Due to financial difficulties in the late fifties, the local moved yet again, this time to a bar owned by Joe Westray, then president of the local. They remained at this location until 1965.
The presidents of Local 471 were elected by the members for a two year term, with no limit to the number of terms a president could serve. Records of the names of earlier presidents have been lost. The earliest known president was Hence "Prez" Jackson from the early thirties to the mid-forties at which point Stoney Gloster served until 1954. In 1954 Carl Arter served until 1958 when Joe Westray became president and filled that office until the merge deposed him in 1965. He became one of the three representatives from 471 to serve on the board of the merged local, along with Carl Arter and Rubye Younge Hardy.
The merge was prompted by the American Federation of Musicians integration policy of that time. Pittsburgh could no longer operate two locals, separated on the basis of race. The merger appears to have cost the African American union members much of their autonomy. Leadership positions remained for the most part in the hands of the white musicians. Many of 471's membership cards and records were also lost with the merger costing a great number of the members' benefits from their seniority in the union. It was at this point many African American musicians cancelled their membership in the union, which meant that they could no longer play music professionally in Pittsburgh.
History of the African American Jazz Preservation Society of Pittsburgh
The African American Jazz Preservation Society of Pittsburgh was incorporated in 1996 after a group of Pittsburgh's senior African American Jazz, Blues and Gospel musicians formed a committee to look into the recovery of the lost history of Local 471. Under the leadership of Charles E. Austin the society's main direction has been towards the oral history project and in filing a discrimination civil action suit. The society publishes Jazz Notes, which has been a forum for education, opportunity and rediscovery of the former union's history.
Scope and Content Notes
This oral history collection consists of transcripts, cassette tapes, project working files and background organizational records of the interviews conducted during the AAJPSP Oral History Project. The AAJPSP Oral History Project documents individual African American Jazz Musicians in Pittsburgh as well as their efforts to organize. The content of the interviews span from 1904 to 1999.
The project conducted by volunteers was an effort to document and preserve the cultural, economic, social and educational contributions of the union, from the perspectives of the African American Jazz, Blues, and Gospel artists who organized, operated and benefited from its programs and activities. Volunteer musicians interviewed former members of the union throughout the Pittsburgh region.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Charles E. Austin, President (AAJPSP), 1998.
Previous Citation
African American Jazz Preservation Society of Pittsburgh Oral History Project, 1995-1999, AIS.1998.04, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
African American Jazz Preservation Society of Pittsburgh Oral History Project, 1995-1999, UE 98:4, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Music; Musicians; Releases; Audiotapes; Transcripts; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Race relations; African American musicians -- Labor unions -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; African Americans -- Segregation -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; African American musicians -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Biography; African American jazz musicians -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Jazz -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History and criticism; Labor; Societies; Ethnic groups; Aarons, Al; Afro-American Musical Association of Pittsburgh; American Federation of Musicians. Local 471 (Pittsburgh, Pa); American Federation of Musicians. Local 60 (Pittsburgh, Pa); American Federation of Musicians. Local 60-471 (Pittsburgh, Pa); Arter, Carl; Austin, Charles E.; Austin, Wilbert; Barnett, David K.; Betters, Harold; Betters, Jerry; Boswell, Robert; Brooks, Alyce; Burns, William N.; Cook, Adolph D.; Cotton, William W.; Cottrell, Charles; Dunn, Nathaniel; Fisher, Kenny; Gambrell, Bill; Harper, Walt; Harris, Joe; Harris,, Joseph; Henderson, Pete; Hill, Hermon J.; Holt, Harold K.; Hughes, John; Humphries, Lawrence G.; Humphries, Roger; Jones, Roy E.; Kelly, Marcus L.; Kemp, Jesse; Kennedy, Joe, violinist; Laley, Daniel; Lee, David; Lee, Harold W.; McCown, Frank; McDaniel, Thomas, T.; McKay, Delsey; McMahan, Bass; Moody, Willis T.; Murphy, Carl; Musicians Protective Union (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Nance, Art; Nelson, Frank, African American jazz musician; Odum, Joseph G.; Patton, Joseph; Payne, James H.; Pittsburgh Musical Society; Pittsburgh Musicians' Union; Pryor, Fred; Smith, Thames Eldridge; Spaulding, George H.; Steath, Oliver C.; Thomas, John, African American jazz musician; Thompson, George; Turrentine, Stanley; Watson, J. Warren; Webster, Robin; Westray, Joe; Elliott, Jerry; Young, Curtis; Brooks, Cecil, II; Younge-Hardy, Rubye
- Interviews, 1995-1999; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The audio cassettes are arranged alphabetically.
  - Aarons, Al-, November 27, 1999 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 1)
  - Arter, Carl-, October 5, 1995 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 2)
  - Austin, Charles E.-, August 2, 1995 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 3)
  - Austin, Will-, July 15, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 4)
  - Barnett, David-, March 13, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 5)
  - Betters, Harold-, March 22, 1996 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 6)
  - Betters, Jerry-, July 1-2, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 7, 8)
  - Boswell, Bobby-, April 22, 1996 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 9)
  - Brooks, Alyce-, June 24, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 10)
  - Brooks, Cecil II-, October 24, 1995 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 11)
  - Burns, Bill-, July 29, 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 12)
  - Cook, Adolph D.-, August 12, 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 13)
  - Cotton, Bill-, February 29, 1996 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 14)
  - Cottrell, Chuck-, January 29, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 15, 16)
  - Dunn, Nathaniel (Tinky)-, September 19, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 17)
  - Elliott, Jerry-, July 25, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 18)
  - Fisher, Kenny-, July 28, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 19)
  - Gambrell, Jacques "Bill"-, May 8, 1995 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 20)
  - Hardy, Rubye Younge-, December 10, 1996 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 21)
  - Harper, Walt-, July 21, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 22)
  - Harris, Joe, 1926-, December 6, 1995 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 23)
  - Harris, Joseph Jr. 1928-, August 7, 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 24)
  - Henderson, Pete-, March 8, 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 25)
  - Hill, Herman-, September 23, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 26)
  - Holt, Harold K.-, February 13, 1996 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 27, 28)
  - Hughes, John-, April 14, 1996 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 29)
  - Hughes, John-, May 25, 1996 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 30)
  - Humphries, Lawrence-, July 8, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 31)
  - Humphries, Roger-, August 8, 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 32)
  - Jones, Roy-, March 12, 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 33)
  - Kelly, Marcus-, April 16, 1996 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 34)
  - Kemp, Jesse-, December 15, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 35)
  - Kennedy, Joe Jr.-, September 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-3, Cassette 36)
  - Laley, Dan-, November 2, 1996 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 37, 38)
  - Lee, Dave-, March 6, 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 39)
  - Lee, Harold-, July 3, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 40)
  - McCown, Frank-, July 16, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 41)
  - McDaniel, Tommy-, March 9, 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 42)
  - McKay, Delsey-, March 31, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 43, 44)
  - McMahon, William "Bass"-, August 24, 1995 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 45)
  - Moody, Willis-, August 22, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 46)
  - Murphy, Carl, "Tape is completely blank." (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 47)
  - Nance, Art-, October 5, 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 48)
  - Nelson, Frank-, July 26, 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 49)
  - Odum, Joe-, September 17, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 50)
  - Patton, Joe-, July 25, 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 51)
  - Payne, James-, July 31, 1998 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 52)
  - Pryor, Fred-, July 29, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 53)
  - Smith, Eldridge-, July 10, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 54)
  - Spaulding, George Duke-, June 28, 1995 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 55)
  - Spaulding, George Duke-, October 2, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cabinet 56)
  - Steath, Ollie-, July 19, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 57)
  - Thomas, John-, May 27, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 58)
  - Thompson, George-, Feburary 23, 1996 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cabinet 59)
  - Thompson, George-, December 3, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 60)
  - Turrentine, Stanley-, November 23, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 61)
  - Watson, Judge Warren-, February 10, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 62)
  - Webster, Robin-, September 25, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 63)
  - Westray, Joe-, November 13, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 64)
  - Young, Curtis-, June 9, 1995 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 65)
  - Young, Curtis-, August 25, 1995 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 66)
  - Young, Curtis-, September 20, 1995 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 67)
  - Young, Curtis-, Feburary 19, 1996 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 68)
  - Young, Curtis-, March 29, 1996 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 69)
  - Young, Curtis-, June 17, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 70)
  - Young, Curtis-, August 13, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 71)
  - Young, Curtis-, November 28, 1997 (Audio-cabinet 3-5, Cassette 72)
- Transcripts, 1995-1999; II.
  - Aaron, Al interviewed by Charles E. Austin, November 27, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Aarons, Albert, a trumpet player who performed in Pittsburgh and recorded music in California.
    [T1S1] Beginning music; joining Local 471; musical inspiration; Army; racism; day jobs; jazz band in high school; big bands; Local 471 politics; advice to younger musicians; recording in California; advice for studio recording.
  - Arter, Carl interviewed by Charles E. Austin, October 5, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Arter, Carl, a saxophone and piano player who performed in Pittsburgh and was a Local 471 President.
    [T1S1] Pittsburgh bands; racism in Oklahoma; MGM contract; dance hall; intimidation of New York City; Silvertones; other musicians; Nate Harper's band; transcription jobs.
    [T1S2] Other musicians; touring; record shop and recording studio; reuniting with old musician friends; family and music; childhood and beginning piano; day jobs; relationships with other musicians; Jazz Beat Show.
  - Austin, Charles E. interviewed by Cathy Cairns, August 2, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Austin, Charles E., a trumpeter who toured with Lloyd Price, his own band in Pittsburgh, and stayed involved with the Musicians' Union after the merger.
    [T1S1] Childhood and music; high school band; Navy; Union camaraderie; Carnival; studying music; touring with Lloyd Price; competition between bands; Chuck Austin Quintet; rehearsal bands; childhood inspiration; reading music; merger and pensions; old Musicians' Club.
    [T1S2] Jam sessions; club associate members; advice to younger musicians; influence on younger musicians; importance of rehearsal bands and reading music; changes in music business; effect of recordings.
  - Austin, Wilbert interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 15, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Austin, Will, a trumpeter who played for the National Guard for six years, played and composed music in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Junior and high school musical career; National Guard; studying and writing music; National Guard; studying music; Union; musical composition and recordings; Union and Musicians' Club; studying music; different horn models and quality.
    [T1S2] New Years performances; work and pensions; performing with other musicians; advice for younger musicians.
  - Barnett, David interviewed by Charles E. Austin, March 13, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Barnett, David, a trumpet and baritone horn player who was a bandleader and performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Local 471 history; joining the union; best moments of performing; beginning music; Army; trumpet players; Barnett's band; Local 471 politics; performing at AFL-CIO merge convention; other musicians; Union merger; touring and the black theater circuit; switching to baritone and performances.
    [T1S2] Barnett's band; relatives; Elks band members; old Musicians' Club; booking jobs and rival bandleaders; other musicians; AAJPSP oral history project; performing at sporting events.
  - Betters, Harold interviewed by Charles E. Austin, March 22, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Bettors, Harold, a trombone player who was a bandleader and performed in Pittsburgh, New York and Washington D.C.
    [T1S1] Musical family; joining Local 471; Army; Musicians' Club history; Army; touring with band and importance of traveling; suburban high school music programs; booking jobs; music schools; early performances in Pittsburgh; problems with Union; Union members.
    [T1S2] purpose of AAJPSP oral history project; current Union politics.
  - Betters, Jerry interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 1, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Bettors, Jerry (July 1, 1997) a percussionist and charismatic band leader who had a popular club in Pittsburgh after his time touring and performing in New York.
    [T1S1] music and childhood; Local 471, Local 60 and their merger; racism in the clubs; playing at Pittsburgh clubs; Jerry Bettors Club; meeting Frank Sinatra; performing in New York; friendship with Anne Baker; drums studio in New York.
    [T1S2] advice to younger musicians; inspirational musicians; camaraderie between musicians; old Club; significance of oral histories project; importance of racial inclusion among musicians
  - Betters, Jerry interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 2, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Bettors, Jerry (July 2, 1997) a percussionist and charismatic band leader who had a popular club in Pittsburgh after his time touring and performing in New York.
    [T1S1] owning his club; importance of being qualified; younger musicians; singers and other musicians; learning in New York City; advice to younger musicians; musical influence; carnival circuit and musical endurance.
  - Boswell, Robert interviewed by Charles E. Austin, April 22, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Boswell, Bobby, a bass player who performed with Billie Holiday and in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Beginning music; early band; joining Local 471; Local 471 and members; jam sessions; other musicians; Army; Billie Holiday's Band; returning to Pittsburgh; Local 471 officers; playing to audience; Walt Harper's Band; transcription jobs.
    [T1S2] Touring with Bradshaw; other musicians; old Musicians' Club importance and layout; downtown clubs; racial tensions between bands; Union merger; changes audience and music; other musicians; Union merger; society bands expectations.
  - Brooks, Alyce interviewed by Cathy Cairns, June 24, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Brooks, Alyce, a pianist and singer who performed her solo act in lounges in Pittsburgh and around the U.S.
    [T1S1] Childhood; performing in Pittsburgh and Chicago; Pittsburgh lounges; greatest achievement; the Convention; proudest moment; advice for younger musicians; reading music.
    [T1S2] Esteemed musicians and Union members; favorite songs; advice from mother; meeting Erroll Garner.
  - Brooks, Cecil II interviewed by George Thompson, October 24, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Brooks, Cecil, a drummer who toured in Ohio and performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] beginning music playing piano, then drums; joining Local 471 and playing professionally; touring in Ohio; playing with Bobby Jones; relationshipo with Local 471; Musician's club; difficulty musically succeeding in Pittsburgh; racism in Pittsburgh; disgust with Union; economic problems affect availability of jobs; monetary corruption; advice to younger musicians; importance of drummer in a band.
  - Burns, Bill interviewed by George Thompson, July 29, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Burns, Bill, a guitar player from a musical family who performed in New York and was a band leader in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Musical family and beginning music; time in the Army; performing in New York; Union 802; joining Local 471; starting band; mentor; playing in Pittsburgh; new Musicians' Club; childhood inspirations; importance of practicing; Pittsburgh clubs.
    [T1S2] Lessons and reading music; musical influence; performing for church; quitting and returning; Union politics and merger; transcription jobs; being a band leader; importance of traveling; other musicians; advice for younger musicians.
  - Cook, Adolph Doug interviewed by Charles E. Austin, August 12, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Cook, Adolph Doug, piano player who was a bandleader in the Army, and performed in Pittsburgh and Michigan.
    [T1S1] Beginning music; Army; territory bands; relationship with Local 471 members; the Musician's Club; WPA Bands; segregation in the Army; enlisting in the Army.
    [T1S2] Other piano players and bands; performing in Pittsburgh; other musicians and style of playing; Local 56 (Grand Rapids); performing in Michigan; advice to younger musicians; performing for weddings.
  - Cotton, William interviewed by Charles E. Austin, February 29, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Cotton, William, a piano player and singer who was a bandleader and performed in Pittsburgh. [T1S1] Beginning music; learning from musicians; joining a union; time in the service; music school in Pittsburgh; performing in Pittsburgh; early exposure to music; touring; photographs; booking jobs; Local 471 members and Pittsburgh clubs.
    [T1S2] Downtown clubs; problems with Local 471; Union merger; Local 471 officers; Pittsburgh clubs; bandleader responsibilities; 50 year card and Union pension; playing to the crowd; Union merge and loss of musicians; racial relations and clubs.
  - Cottrell, Charles interviewed by Charles E. Austin, January 29, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Cottrell, Charles, a piano player who performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Music and childhood; Army; learning from musicians; influential musicians; Local 471 clique; performing in Pittsburgh; traveling; changes from the Union merge. [T1S2] Post-merger politics; transcription jobs; advice to younger musicians; carnival shows; importance of fellowship and sharing with younger musicians; touring; Local 471 officers; significance of musician fellowship and playing music
    [T2S1] performing in Pittsburgh clubs; other musicians.
  - Dunn, Nathaniel "Tinky" interviewed by Charles E. Austin, September 19, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Dunn, Nathaniel "Tinky," a bass player who joined the Union in 1939, had a band and played in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Music in childhood and lessons; playing in Pittsburgh clubs in early years; relationship with union members; transcription and WPA Bands; New Union and MPT; Dunn's first group; writing music; religion and childhood; old club; history of union and members. [T1S2] Importance of reading music; involvement in Union; effects of new club; playing in Pittsburgh clubs; teaching music and Austin's (Interviewer) childhood; advice for younger musicians; gospel music.
  - Elliot, Jerry interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 25, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Elliott, Jerry, a trombone player who began playing piano while in the service, played piano and wrote music in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Junior and high school musical career; time in the Army; Joe Westray's Band; brass instrument mouthpiece technique; the Union and the Musicians' Club; piano and trombone; writing music; difference between old and new Club; playing with other musicians.
    [T1S2] Special gigs; Pittsburgh's Musicians' Club comparison; disparity between inner-city and suburban schools; lack of leadership in young generation; drug problems; daytime jobs; importance of upbringing; technique players; advice for younger musicians.
  - Fisher, Kenny interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 28, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Fisher, Kenny, a tenor saxophone player who wrote music and performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Beginning music; Union merge; East Liberty Musicians' Club and musicians; private lessons; bands and Local 471 members; big bands; influential musicians; Union merge politics; traveling; teaching music to young students.
    [T1S2] Jazz sessions; high school years; father's musical career; bands and bandleader.
  - Gambrell, Jacques "Bill" interviewed by Charles E. Austin, May 8, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Gambrell, Bill, a piano and organ player who was an active member of the Local 471 and performed in Pittsburgh.